After making over a thousand pints in
the Ninja Creamy, I have finally cracked
the code on how to get any texture you
want. Whether you want hard ice cream,
soft serve, Dairy Queen Blizzards,
McDonald's McFlurries, it all comes down
to these five factors. One, the
ingredients you use in your base. In
general, the more protein or fat you put
in your base, the thicker and creamier
it will be. So, adding things like
protein powder or cream cheese or peanut
butter will really help the texture out.
But using watery liquids like almond
milk or a lot of these other non-dairy
milks can severely impact the texture
and make it very icy. To combat that,
you can use binding agents like zantham
gum or guar gum. These things bind ice
crystals together and make for a better
mouth feel and more ice cream like
texture. Before I ramble about this for
20 minutes, let's move on to number two.
Freeze time. This is the number one
cause of all comments that I get that
say, "My pint is too soupy. The texture
is too soft. What happened?" If you're
not freezing for at least 16 hours in a
cold freezer, you are not going to get
hard ice cream. And ideally, you freeze
for at least 24. If you pull your pint
out of the freezer and it does not look
completely frozen solid through like a
block, it's not ready. Three spin
settings. Now, we're moving on to the
spinning process. So, each spin setting
actually spins at a different rate and
amount of time. If you're making protein
ice cream, like most of the recipes I
make, you're going to want to do a
longer setting, like light ice cream or
sorbet. This is because these bases
freeze harder than normal ice cream
because you're not using the same fat
content or sugar content. So, you need
more time and more processing power.
Screenshot these charts and print them
out for further reference. Four, let's
talk about handling. So, what you do
with your pint after you take it out of
the freezer. I always say to run your
pine under hot water for 30 to 60
seconds or leave it out on the counter
for 5 to 10 minutes. The entire goal
here is to melt the ice crystals off of
the side of the pint. But if you do
these things for too long, that will
likely lead to a very soupy pint. Five
mixins. These are generally not a huge
factor, but they can ruin a pint. If you
mix in something very watery, like fresh
fruit, I guarantee the texture will come
out softer than you want it to be. I've
actually found that freezing your
mix-ins works wonders for controlling
the texture, and it also helps them stay
intact. If you're familiar with using
the mix-ins setting, you know, it
obliterates all soft mixins, but frozen
mix-ins generally hold up pretty well.
So, what I like to do is chop my mixins
up into my desired size and then freeze
them and then just add all of those in
as a mixin. And the final tip, follow
me. If you guys aren't following me yet
and you have a Ninja Creamy, I have no
idea what you're doing. I'm posting new
recipes, tips, tricks every single day.
So follow along and try some of my
recipes